Finding Aid for Huron Valley Girl Scout Council records, circa 1940-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Huron Valley Girl Scout Council records circa 1940-1965
Huron Valley Girl Scout Council.
7 linear feet
851344 Bj 2
Administrative files, including board and finance minutes, agendas, fund-raising and promotional materials, scrapbooks, articles of incorporation, and other miscellanea; also files of the Ypsilanti, Wayne, and Brighton, Michigan, councils of the Girl Scouts.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor no. 5259 ) was donated by the Huron Valley Girl Scout Council in June 1972.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Since 1940 the Girl Scouts have been a tradition in southeastern Michigan. The membership has grown significantly over the years.
In July 1958 the Ann Arbor, Plymouth and Washtenaw County Girl Scout Councils combined to form the Huron Valley Girl Scout Council.
The Huron Valley Girl Scout Council was chartered by the Girl Scouts of the U.S.A. and is responsible for all girl scouting within its two and one-half county jurisdiction of Western Wayne, Washtenaw and Livingston.
The Huron Valley Girl Scout Council is governed by a Board of Directors responsible for administering scouting within the Council. The Board is composed of all District Chairmen, Officers of the Council, Chairmen of Standing Committees, and Members-at-Large.
The Huron Valley Girl Scout Council is comprised of four districts which are further divided into thirty-four neighborhoods. For each neighborhood, there is an association composed of all registered adults active in that neighborhood. Each month, the neighborhood chairmen in each district meet to provide the opportunity for each active Girl Scout adult working with troops in the neighborhood to participate in the development of Council plans.
The Huron Valley Girl Scout Council has a professional staff consisting of an Executive Director and the District Directors. The Executive Director is responsible for staff members and works with the Board, Finance Council, and several committees. Each of the four District Directors works with one of the four districts and one or more committees.
The Council is administratively and financially autonomous. Responsibility for financing the work of the council belongs to the board of directors, which usually delegates this function to the finance committee. The Council derives a major portion of its income from various fees from members and voluntary contributions. Contributions come directly to the council as unsolicited gifts, as the result of a fund-raising campaign, or as an allocation from the eighteen local Community Chests or the United Fund.
The Huron Valley Girl Scout Council record group documents the administration and activities of a growing Girl Scout Council in Michigan. It is comprised of such records as Board and Council minutes, by-laws, annual reports, newsletters, financial material, various committee minutes, district files, promotional material, annual agendas, membership information, and staff position descriptions. Included in the records are the files of the Ann Arbor, Plymouth and Washtenaw County Girl Scout Councils. In 1958 these agencies combined to form the Huron Valley Girl Scout Council. The records cover the years 1940 through 1965 with the bulk covering 1958-1962. Only a portion of the records have been processed. Those materials which have been processed consist of the following series: Ann Arbor Girl Scout Council, Plymouth Girl Scout Council, Girl Scout Council of Washtenaw County and Huron Valley Girl Scout Council.
Subjects:
Brighton (Mich.); Girl Scouts.; Scouting (Youth activity)--Michigan.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Wayne (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Ann Arbor Girl Scout Council
  The Ann Arbor Girl Scout Council series (0.25 linear feet) spans the years 1940-1957 (bulk 1952-1954). The records consist of the Council's Article of Incorporation and a scattering of annual reports, board minutes, finance material, newsletters and membership directories.
  - Annual reports 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Article of Incorporation February 2, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Board Minutes 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Finances 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - Membership Directories 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1949-1957 (Box 1)
- Plymouth Girl Scout Council
  The Plymouth Girl Scout Council series (0.125 linear feet) spans the years 1943-1953. This small series consists of one small typed book of minutes arranged in chronological order and one scrapbook filled with dated newspaper clippings featuring Plymouth's Troop #1.
  - Book of Minutes 1943-1949 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1943-1953 (Box 1)
- Girl Scout Council of Washtenaw County
  The Girl Scout Council of Washtenaw County series (0.125 linear feet) spans the years 1955-1958. The records in this small series consist of annual reports, board minutes, by-laws, finance material and a Board of Directors List.
  - Annual Reports 1955, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Board Minutes 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors List circa 1955 (Box 1)
  - By-Laws circa 1955 (Box 1)
  - Finances 1955-1958 (Box 1)
- Huron Valley Girl Scout Council
  - Administrative Files
    - Annual Report 1960 (Box 1)
    - By-Laws/Background Information circa 1958 (Box 1)
    - Board Minutes 1958-1964, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Council Minutes 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - Committee Minutes
      - Camp Committee 1960-1964 (Box 1)
      - Field Committee 1960-1962 (Box 1)
      - Finance Committee 1958-1964 (Box 1)
      - Membership-Nominating Committee 1958-1964 (Box 1)
      - Program Committee 1959-1964 (Box 1)
      - Public Relations Committee 1959-1962 (Box 1)
      - Training Committee 1959-1960 (Box 1)
      - Troop Organization Committee 1958-1963 (Box 1)
  - District Committee Minutes
    - District I 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - District II 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - District III 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - District IV 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  - Publicity
    - Camp Brochures and Manuals 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, circa 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - "Gleanings From the President" November 1963 (Box 1)
    - "Huron Valley Echo" 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    - Memos to Neighborhood Chairmen 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - Radio and Television Promotional Skit Scripts (Box 1)
  - Topical Files
    - Activities
      - Girl Scout Week 1961 (Box 1)
      - Senior Round-up 1961 (Box 1)
    - Goals
      - Plans of Work and Budget-Annual Committee Agendas 1959-1961 (Box 1)
      - Workbooks-Annual Meeting Agendas and Election Worksheets 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    - Membership
      - Development Committee Membership Questionnaires-Used in Council Reorganization 1957 (Box 2)
      - Membership and Population Surveys 1958-1959 (Box 2)
      - Membership Analyses 1960-1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Staff
      - Council Job Descriptions (Box 2)
      - Public Relations Job Descriptions 1961 (Box 2)
    - Studies/Reports
      - Drop-Out Study-Studied the reasons why some girls quit Scouting 1959 (Box 2)
      - Relationship With Archdiocese of Detroit 1959 (Box 2)
        An effort to encourage scouting among Catholic girls.
  - Unprocessed and unfoldered 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Unprocessed and unfoldered 1960-1963 (Box 3)
  - Unprocessed 1963 (Box 4)
  - Unprocessed and unfoldered 1963 (Box 5)
  - Unprocessed, various dates (Box 5)
  - Unprocessed 1963 (Box 6)
  - Local chapter records
    - Ann Arbor (Box 6)
    - Brighton (Box 6)
    - Chelsea (Box 6)
    - Washtenaw County, Michigan (Box 7)
    - Wayne, Michigan (Box 7)
    - Ypsilanti (Box 7)